<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Parabuild 4.4</title>

  <subtitle>User&#39;s Manual</subtitle>

  <bookinfo>
    <copyright>
      <year>2017</year>

      <holder>Parabuild CI</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Build Statuses Page</title>

    <para>Build statuses page shows configured builds and their current
    statuses. The page refreshes automatically every thirty seconds. The
    content of the page depends on the &#34;page view&#34; mode. There are two
    view modes: list view and detailed view. To switch between these modes
    click &#34;List view&#34; or &#34;Detailed view&#34; links respectively.
    Differences between the modes are considered below.</para>

    <section>
      <title>List View Mode</title>

      <para>This mode allows to see an overview of all build statuses on a
      single page. It is suitable for ongoing build statuses monitoring. When
      in the list view mode, the build statuses page shows a table with a list
      of builds and their current statuses (waiting, building, etc.) and a
      link to the page with the last build result, if any. The link is in red
      if the last build failed or in green if the last build was successful. A
      caption of the link tells the last build number and time.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Detailed View Mode</title>

      <para>This mode allows monitoring of the detailed status of a selected
      build. In the detailed view the page it is split into two parts. On the
      left side there is a vertical navigation bar that allows selecting a
      particular build to view. The right side of the page contains detailed
      information about the current build status including:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Build name with the current build status.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Currently running build steps.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Links to the last build result including build logs, error
          quotes, and changes in the last build, build history, date and time
          of the last build.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Link to the last clean build, if any.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>List of changes in the currently running build (or changes in
          the last build if the build is not running).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Disabling Page Refresh</title>

      <para>To provide online infromation about build statuses the build
      status page refreshes automatically. To disable automatic refresh click
      on &#34;Turn refresh OFF&#34; link. The link can be found in the top
      right corner of the status page. Once the refresh is disabled, the links
      changes its caption to &#34;Turn refresh ON&#34;. Clicking on this links
      will re-enable the automatic refresh of the builds status page.<figure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
      align="center" fileref="refresh_on_off.gif"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting Page Refresh Rate</title>

      <para>By default the page refresh rate is set to 10 seconds. To set
      refresh rate of the build status page log in to Parabuild and select
      &#34;Preferences&#34; link on the top navigation bar:<figure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
      align="center" fileref="preferences_link.gif"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para>

      <para>A form with your personal preferences will open. Fill &#34;Build
      status refresh rate&#34; field and click on &#34;Save&#34; button:<figure><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
      align="center" fileref="setting_refresh_rate.gif"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>