<!-- $Id: sqltool.xml,v 1.58 2004/10/20 01:46:51 unsaved Exp $ -->

<chapter id='sqltool-chapter'>
    <title id='sqltool-title'>SqlTool</title>
    <subtitle>SqlTool Manual</subtitle>
    <chapterinfo>
        <author>
            <firstname>Blaine</firstname><surname>Simpson</surname>
            <email>&blaineaddr;</email>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>HSQLDB Development Group</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <edition>$Revision: 1.58 $</edition>
        <pubdate>$Date: 2004/10/20 01:46:51 $</pubdate>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>SqlTool</keyword>
            <keyword>HSQLDB</keyword>
            <keyword>SQL</keyword>
            <keyword>JDBC</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>

    <section>
        <title>Purpose</title>
        <simpara>
            This document explains how to use SqlTool, the main purpose of
            which is to read your SQL text file or stdin, and execute the SQL 
            commands therein against a JDBC database.
            There are also a great number of features to facilitate both
            interactive use (such as command-line editing and aliases) and 
            automation (such as scripting variables and SQL transaction 
            control and error handling).
        </simpara><simpara>
            Some of the examples below use quoting which works exactly
            as-is for any normal UNIX shell.
            I have not yet tested these commands on Windows, and I doubt
            whether the quoting will work just like this (though it is
            possible).
            SqlTool is still a very useful tool even if you have no quoting
            capability at all.
        </simpara><simpara>
            This document is now updated for version 1.37 of SqlTool and
            1.86 of SqlFile (the latter is the class which does most of the
            work for SqlTool).
            The startup banner will report both versions when you run SqlTool
            interactively.
            I expect this version of this document to accurately describe 
            SqlTool for some unknown number of versions into the future.
        </simpara>
    </section>

    <section id='baremin-section'>
        <title>The Bare Minimum You Need to Know to Run SqlTool</title>
        <titleabbrev id='baremin-title'>The Bare Minimum</titleabbrev>
        <simpara>
            If you want to use SqlTool, then you either have an SQL text file, 
            or you want to interactively type in SQL commands.
            If neither case applies to you, then you are looking at the wrong 
            program.
        </simpara>
            <procedure>
                <title>To run SqlTool...</title>
                <step><simpara>
                    Copy the file <filename>sqltool.rc</filename> from the
                    directory <filename>src/org/hsqldb/sample</filename> of 
                    your HSQLDB distribution
                    to your home directory and
                    secure access to it if your home directory is accessible
                    to anybody else.
                    This file will work as-is for a Memory Only database
                    instance; or if your target is a HSQLDB Server 
                    running on your local computer with default settings
                    and the password for the "sa" account is blank
                    (the sa password is blank when new HSQLDB database 
                    instances are created).
                    Edit the file if you need to change the target Server URL, 
                    username, password, character set, JDBC driver, or TLS 
                    trust store as documented in the 
                    <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section.
                </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                    Find out where your hsqldb.jar file resides.
                    It typically resides at
<emphasis role='bold'>HSQLDB_HOME</emphasis><filename>/lib/hsqldb.jar</filename>
                    where <emphasis role='bold'>HSQLDB_HOME</emphasis> is the
                    base directory of your HSQLDB software installation.
                    For this reason, I'm going to use 
                    "$HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar" as the path to
                    <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename> for my examples, but 
                    understand that you need to use the actual path to your
                    own <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename> file.
                </simpara></step><step><para>
                    Run 
                <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar --help</screen>
                </informalexample>
                    to see what command-line arguments are available.
                    Note that you don't need to worry about setting the 
                    CLASSPATH when you use the <literal>-jar</literal> switch
                    to <filename>java</filename>.
                    Assuming that you set up your SqlTool configuration file 
                    at the default location and you want to use the HSQLDB 
                    JDBC driver, you will want to run something like
                <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar mem</screen>
                </informalexample>
                    for interactive use, or
                <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar --noinput --sql 'SQL statement;' mem</screen>
                    </informalexample>
                    or
                    <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar mem filepath1.sql...</screen>
                    </informalexample>
                    where <literal>mem</literal> is an
                    <emphasis>urlid</emphasis>,
                    and the following arguments are paths to text SQL files.
                    For the filepaths, you can use whatever wildcards your 
                    operating system shell supports.
                    </para><simpara>
                    The <emphasis>urlid</emphasis> <literal>mem
                    </literal>in these commands is a key 
                    into your SqlTool configuration file, as explained in the 
                    <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section.
                    Since this is a Memory Only database, you can use SqlTool
                    with this urlid immediately with no database setup 
                    whatsoever (however, you can't persist any changes that 
                    you make to this database).
                    The sample sqltool.rc file also defines the urlid
                    "localhost-sa" for a local HSQLDB Server.
                    At the end of this section, I explain how you can load
                    some sample data to play with, if you want to.
                </simpara></step>
            </procedure>
        <important><simpara>
            SqlTool does not <emphasis>commit</emphasis> DML changes by default.
            This leaves it to the user's disgression whether to commit or
            rollback their modifications.
            Remember to either run the command <literal>commit;</literal>
            before quitting SqlTool, or use the <literal>--autoCommit</literal>
            command-line switch.
        </simpara></important>
        <simpara>
            Note that the <literal>--sql</literal> switch runs the given
            commands <emphasis>in addition</emphasis> to standard input
            and/or specified SQL files.
            If you want to run only SQL command(s) which you give on the
            command-line, then use the <literal>--sql</literal> switch
            <emphasis>and</emphasis> the <literal>--noinput</literal> switch.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            If you put a file named <filename>auto.sql</filename> into your
            home directory, this file will be executed automatically every
            time that you run SqlTool interactively and without the
            <literal>--noAutoFile</literal> switch.
        </simpara> <para>
            To use a JDBC Driver other than the HSQLDB driver, you can't use
            the <literal>-jar</literal> switch because you need to modify the
            classpath.
            You must add the hsqldb.jar file and your JDBC driver classes to
            your classpath,
            and you must tell SqlTool what the JDBC driver class name is.
            The latter can be accomplished by either using the "--driver" 
            switch, or setting "driver" in your config file.
            The <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section.
            explains the second method.  Here's an example of the first method
            (after you have set the classpath appropriately).
        <informalexample><screen>
java org.hsqldb.util.SqlTool --driver oracle.jdbc.OracleDriver urlid</screen>
        </informalexample></para>
        <tip><simpara>
            If the tables of query output on your screen are all messy 
            because of lines wrapping, the best and easiest solution
            is usually to resize your terminal emulator window to make it
            wider.
            (With some terms you click &amp; drag the frame edges to resize,
            with others you use a menu system where you can enter the number
            of columns).
        </simpara></tip>
        <para>
            If you want some sample database objects and data to play with,
            execute the <filename>sampledata.sql</filename> SQL file.
            <filename>sampledata.sql</filename> resides in the
            <filename>src/org/hsqldb/sample</filename> directory of your
            HSQLDB distribution.
            Run it like this from an SqlTool session
    <programlisting>\i HSQLDB_HOME/src/org/hsqldb/sample/sampledata.sql</programlisting>
            where <emphasis role='bold'>HSQLDB_HOME</emphasis> is the
            base directory of your HSQLDB software installation.
        </para>
            For memory-only databases, you'll need to run this every time that
            you run SqlTool.
            For other (persistent) databases, the data will reside in your
            database until you drop the tables.
    </section>

    <section id='auth-section'>
        <title id='auth-title'>Authentication Setup</title>
        <simpara>
            Authentication setup is accomplished by creating a text SqlTool
            configuration file.
            In this section, when I say <emphasis>configuration</emphasis>
            or <emphasis>config</emphasis> file, I mean an SqlTool 
            configuration file (aka SqlTool RC file).
        </simpara><simpara>
            The following sample <filename>sqltool.rc</filename> file resides
            in the directory <filename>src/org/hsqldb/sample</filename> of your
            HSQLDB distribution.
        </simpara>
        <example>
            <title>Sample sqltool.rc File</title>
            <programlisting>&sqltool.rc-cdata;</programlisting>
        </example>
        <para>
            You can put this file anywhere you want to, and specify the 
            location to SqlTool by using the "--rcfile" argument.
            If there is no reason to not use the default location (and there 
            are situations where you would not want to), then use the default
            location and you won't have to give "--rcfile" arguments to 
            SQLTool.
            The default location is <emphasis>sqltool.rc</emphasis> in your 
            home directory.
            If you have any doubt about where that is, then just run SqlTool 
            with a phony urlid and it will tell you where it expects the 
            configuration file to be.
        <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar x</screen>
        </informalexample></para><para>
            The config file consists of stanza(s) like this:
        <informalexample><screen>
    urlid web
    url jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://localhost
    username web
    password webspassword</screen>
        </informalexample></para><para>
            These four settings are required for every urlid.
            (There are optional settings also, which are described a couple 
            paragraphs down).
            You can have as many blank lines and comments like
        <informalexample><screen>
    # This comment</screen>
        </informalexample>
        </para><simpara>
            in the file as you like.
            The whole point is that the <emphasis>urlid</emphasis> that you 
            give in your SqlTool command must match a <emphasis>urlid
            </emphasis> in your configuration file.
        </simpara><important><simpara>
            Use whatever facilities are at  your disposal to protect your 
            configuration file.
        </simpara></important><simpara>
            It should be readable, both locally and remotely, only to users 
            who need to use the records in it to run SqlTool.
            On UNIX, this is easily accomplished by using <literal>chmod/chown
            </literal> commands and making sure that it is protected from 
            anonymous remote access (like via NFS, FTP or Samba).
        </simpara><simpara>
            You can also put the following optional settings into a urlid 
            stanza.  The setting will, of course, only apply to that urlid.
        </simpara>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry><term>charset</term><listitem><simpara>
                Sets encoding character set for input.
                See the <link linkend='charencoding-section'
                    endterm='charencoding-title'/> section of the
                <link linkend='nonint-section' endterm='nonint-title'/>
                section.
                You can, alternatively, set this for one SqlTool invocation 
                by setting the system property <property>sqltool.charset
                </property>.
                Defaults to <literal>US-ASCII</literal>.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>driver</term><listitem><simpara>
                Sets the JDBC driver class name.
                You can, alternatively, set this for one SqlTool invocation 
                by using the SqlTool switch <emphasis>--driver</emphasis>.
                Defaults to <emphasis>org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver</emphasis>.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>truststore</term><listitem><simpara>
                TLS trust keystore store file path as documented in the
                <link linkend='tls-chapter' endterm='tls-title'/> chapter.
                You usually only need to set this if the server is using a
                non-publicly-certified certificate (like a self-signed 
                self-ca'd cert).
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <simpara>
            Property and SqlTool command-line switches override settings made 
            in the configuration file.
        </simpara>
    </section>

    <section id='int-section'>
        <title id='int-title'>Interactive</title>
        <para>
            Do read the
            <link linkend='baremin-section' endterm='baremin-title'/>
            section before you read this section.
        </para>
        <para>
            You run SqlTool interactively by specifying no SQL filepaths on 
            the SqlTool command line.  Like this.
        <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid</screen>
        </informalexample></para><procedure>
            <title>What happens when SqlTool is run interactively
                (using all default settings)
            </title>
            <step><simpara>
                SqlTool starts up and connects to the specified database,
                using your SqlTool configuration file
                (as explained in the
                <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section).
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                SQL file <filename>auto.sql</filename> in your home directory 
                is executed (if there is one),
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                SqlTool displays a
                banner showing the SqlTool and SqlFile version numbers and 
                describes the different command types that you can give, as 
                well as commands to list all of the specific commands available 
                to you.
            </simpara></step>
        </procedure><simpara>
            You exit your session by using the "\q" special command or ending 
            input (like with Ctrl-D or Ctrl-Z).
        </simpara>
        <important><simpara>
            Every command (regardless of type) and comment must begin at the
            beginning of a line or immediately after a comment ends with
            "*/").
        </simpara><simpara>
            You can't nest commands or comments.
            You can only start new commands (and comments) after the preceding
            statement has been terminated.
            (Remember that you if you're running SqlTool interactively, you 
            can terminate an SQL statement without executing it by entering a
            blank line).
        </simpara><simpara>
            (Special Commands, Buffer Commands and PL Commands always consist
            of just one line.
            Any of these commands or comments may be preceded by space 
            characters.)
        </simpara></important>
        <simpara>
            When you are typing into SqlTool, you are always typing part of
            the <emphasis>current command</emphasis>.
            The <emphasis>buffer</emphasis> is the <emphasis>last SQL 
            command</emphasis>.
            If you're typing an SQL command, then the previous SQL command
            will be in the buffer, not the one you are currently typing.
            The current command could be any type of command, but only SQL
            commands get moved to the buffer when they are completed.
            When you type command-editing commands, the <emphasis>current
            command</emphasis> is the editing command (like
            "<literal>:s/tbl/table/</literal>"), the result of which is to
            modify the SQL command in the buffer (which can thereafter be
            executed).
            The ":a" command (with no argument) is special in that it takes a
            copy of the SQL command in the buffer and makes that the current 
            command, leaving you in a state where you are 
            <emphasis>appending</emphasis> to that 
            <emphasis>now current</emphasis> command.
            The buffer is the zeroeth item of the SQL command history.
        </simpara>
        <variablelist><title>Command types</title>
            <varlistentry><term>SQL Statement</term><listitem><simpara>
                Any command that you enter which does not begin with "\", ":", 
                or "* " is an SQL Statement.
                The command is not terminated when you hit ENTER, like most 
                OS shells.
                You terminate SQL Statements with either ";" at the end of a 
                line, or with a blank line.
                In the former case, the SQL Statement will be executed against 
                the SQL database and the command will go into the command 
                buffer and SQL command history for editing or viewing later on.
                In the latter case (you end an SQL Statement with a blank 
                line), the command will go to the buffer and SQL history, but 
                will not be executed (but you can execute it later from the 
                buffer).
            </simpara><simpara>
                (Blank lines are only interpreted this way when SqlTool is
                run interactively.
                In SQL files, blank lines inside of SQL statements remain
                part of the SQL statement).
            </simpara><simpara>
                As a result of these termination rules, whenever you are 
                entering text that is not a Special Command, Buffer Command, 
                or PL Command, you are always 
                <emphasis>appending</emphasis> lines to an SQL Statement.
                (In the case of the first line, you will be appending to an
                empty SQL statement.  I.e. you will be starting a new SQL 
                Statement).
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>Special Command</term><listitem><simpara>
                Run the command "\?" to list the Special Commands.
                All of the Special Commands begin with "\".
                I'll describe some of the most 
                useful Special Commands below.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>Buffer Command</term><listitem><simpara>
                Run the command ":?" to list the Special Commands.
                All of the Special Commands begin with ":".
                Buffer commands operate upon the command "buffer", so that 
                you can edit and/or (re-)execute previously entered commands.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>PL Command</term><listitem><simpara>
                Procedural Langage commands.
                Run the command "* ?" to list the PL Commands.
                All of the PL Commands begin with "* ".
                PL commands are for setting and using scripting variables
                and conditional and flow control statements like
                <literal>* if</literal> and <literal>* while</literal>.
                Using variables as command aliases (aka macros) can be a real
                convenience for nearly all users, so this feature will be
                discussed briefly in this section.
                More detailed explanation of PL variables and the other 
                PL features, with examples, are covered in the
                <link linkend='pl-section' endterm='pl-title'/> section.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <variablelist><title>Essential Special Commands</title>
            <varlistentry><term>\?</term><listitem><simpara>
                help
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\q</term><listitem><simpara>
                quit
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\dt [filter_substring]</term><listitem><simpara/></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\dv [filter_substring]</term><listitem><simpara/></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\d* [filter_substring]</term><listitem><simpara/></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\ds [filter_substring]</term><listitem><simpara/></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\da [filter_substring]</term><listitem><para>
                Lists available table-like objects of the given type.
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><simpara>t: non-system Tableѕ</simpara></listitem>
                    <listitem><simpara>v: Views</simpara></listitem>
                    <listitem><simpara>*: all table-like objects</simpara></listitem>
                    <listitem><simpara>s: System tableѕ</simpara></listitem>
                    <listitem><simpara>a: database SQL Aliases</simpara></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                If your database supports schemas, then the schema name will
                also be listed.
                </para><simpara>
                If you supply an optional <emphasis>filter substring</emphasis>,
                then only items which contain the given substring (in the object
                name or schema name) will be listed.
                The substring test is case-insensitive.
                </simpara><simpara>
                I do intent to change "\ds" to "\dS".
                I would do it right now if the SqlTool code weren't going
                production in two days.
                The reason is, I want \ds for listing either Sequences (like
                psql) or Synonyms.
            </simpara>
            </listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\d objectname</term><listitem><simpara>
                Lists names of all columns in the specified table or view.
                </simpara><tip><simpara>
                When working with real data (as opposed to learning or playing),
                I often find it useful to run two SqlTool sessions in two
                side-by-side terminal emulator windows.
                I do all of my real work in one window, and use the other
                mostly for \d commands.
                This way I can refer to the data dictionary while writing SQL
                commands, without having to scroll.
            </simpara></tip></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\s</term><listitem><simpara>
                Shows the SQL command history.
                The SQL command history will show a number (a negative number) 
                for each SQL Statement that has made it into the buffer so 
                fare (by either executing or entering a blank line).
                You can then use the "\-" command (which is described next) to 
                retrieve commands from the SQL history to work with.
                To list just the very last command, you would use the ":l" 
                buffer command to list the buffer contents, instead of this 
                command.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>\-[3]</term><listitem><simpara>
                Enter "\" followed by the command number from SQL history, like
                "\-3".
                That command will be written to the buffer so that you can 
                execute it or edit it using buffer commands.
                </simpara><simpara>
                (You can append a semicolon to a recall command in order
                to execute the recalled buffer immediately, like "\-3;".
                This is actually just a shortcut for running the Special
                Command "\-3" and the Buffer Command ":;".)
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <simpara>
            This list here includes only the <emphasis>essential</emphasis> 
            Special Commands, but n.b. that there are other useful Special 
            Commands which you can list by running <literal>\?</literal>.
            (You can, for example, execute SQL from external SQL files, and 
            save your interactive SQL commands to files).
            Some specifics of these other commands are specified immediately 
            below, and the 
            <link linkend='report-section' endterm='report-title'/>
            section explains how to use the "\o" and "\H" special commands to 
            generate reports.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            Be aware that the <literal>\!</literal> Special Command does
            not work for external programs that read from standard input.
            You can invoke non-interactive and graphical interactive programs, 
            but not command-line interactive programs.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            SqlTool executes <literal>\!</literal> programs directly, it does 
            not run an operating system shell (this is to avoid OS-specific
            code in SqlTool).
            Because of this, you can give as many command-line arguments
            as you wish, but you can't use shell wildcards or redirection.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            The \w command can be used to store any command in your SQL 
            history to a file.
            Just restore the command to the buffer (which is the 0th
            element of the history) with a command like "\-4" before you give
            the \w command.
        </simpara>
        <variablelist><title>Buffer Commands</title>
            <varlistentry><term>:?</term><listitem><simpara>
                help
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>:;</term><listitem><simpara>
                Executes the SQL statement in the current buffer against the 
                database.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>:l</term><listitem><simpara>
                (This is a lower case L).
                List the current contents of the buffer.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>:a</term><listitem><simpara>
                Enter append mode with the contents of the buffer as the 
                current SQL Statement.
                Things will be exactly as if you physically re-typed 
                the command that is in the buffer.
                Whatever line you type next will be appended to the SQL 
                Statement.
                You can execute the command by terminating a line with ";",
                or send it back to the buffer by entering a blank line.
                </simpara><simpara>
                You can, optionally, put a string after the :a, in which
                case this text will be appended and you will remain in
                append mode.
                (Unless the text ends with ';', in which case the resultant
                statement will be executed immediately).
                Note that if you do put text after the "a",
                <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> what you type immediately after
                "a" will be appended.
                If your buffer contains
                <literal>SELECT x FROM mytab</literal> and you run
                <literal>a:le</literal>, the resultant command will be
                <literal>SELECT x FROM mytable</literal>.
                If your buffer contains
                <literal>SELECT x FROM mytab</literal> and you run
                <literal>a: ORDER BY y</literal>, the resultant command will be
                <literal>SELECT x FROM mytab ORDER BY y</literal>.
                Notice that in the latter case the append text begins with a
                space character.
            </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>:s/from string/to string/switches</term>
                <listitem>
                <simpara>
                This is the primary command for SqlTool command editing-- 
                it operates upon the current buffer.
                The "to string" and the "switches" are both optional.
                To start with, I'll discuss the use and behavior if you don't
                supply any substitution mode switches.
                </simpara>
                <para>
                Don't use "/" if it occurs in either "from string" or "to 
                string".
                You can use any character that you want in place of "/", but 
                it must not occur in the <emphasis>from</emphasis> or 
                <emphasis>to</emphasis> strings.
                Example
                <informalexample><screen>
    :s@from string@to string@</screen>
                </informalexample></para><simpara>
                The <emphasis>to</emphasis> string is substituted for the first 
                occurrence of the (case-specific)<emphasis>from</emphasis>
                string.
                The replacement will consider the entire SQL statement, even
                if it is a multi-line statement.
                </simpara><para>
                All occurrences of "$" in the <emphasis>from</emphasis> string
                and the <emphasis>to</emphasis> string are treated as line 
                breaks.
                For example, <emphasis>from</emphasis> string of
                "<literal>*$FROM mytable</literal>" would 
                actually look for occurrences of
                <informalexample><screen>
     *
     FROM mytable</screen>
                </informalexample></para><para>
                Here is a another meaningful example using $.
                <informalexample><screen>
    :s/e)$/e) WHERE col1 is not null$/</screen>
                </informalexample></para><simpara>
                This command appends
                "<literal>WHERE col1 is not null</literal>" to the 
                line(s) which end with "e)".
                </simpara><para>
                The <emphasis>to</emphasis> string may be empty, in which case, 
                occurrences of the <emphasis>from</emphasis> string are just 
                deleted.  For example
                <informalexample><screen>
    :s/this//</screen>
                </informalexample></para><simpara>
                would remove the first occurrence of "this".
                (With the "g" substitution mode switch, as explained below,
                it would remove all occurrences of "this").
                </simpara><simpara>
                Don't end a <emphasis>to</emphasis> string with ";" in attempt to make a SQL
                statement execute.
                There is a substitution mode switch to use for that purpose.
                </simpara><para>
                You can use any combination of the substitution mode switches.
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>
                        Use "i" to make the searches for 
                        <emphasis>from</emphasis> string case insensitive.
                    </para></listitem> <listitem><para>
                        Use "g" to substitute globally, i.e., for all 
                        occurrences of <emphasis>from</emphasis> string which 
                        are found in the text under consideration.
                    </para></listitem> <listitem><para>
                        Use ";" to execute the command immediately after the
                        substitution is performed.
                    </para></listitem> <listitem><para>
                        Use an integer (from 1 to 9) to narrow the text under
                        consideration to a specific line of a multi-line
                        buffer.
                    </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <simpara>
                The substitution facility doesn't support any regular
                expressions at all.
                When we stop supporting Java versions older than 1.4, I'll
                start supporting regular expressions and other advanced
                string manipulation functions.
            </simpara> </listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <variablelist><title>Essential PL Command</title>
            <varlistentry><term>* VARNAME = value</term><listitem><simpara>
                Set the value of a variable.
                If the variable doesn't exist yet, it will be created.
            </simpara><para>
                    If you set a variable to an SQL statement (without the
                    terminating ";") you can then use it as an alias like
                    <literal>*VARNAME</literal>, as shown in this example.
                <example id='alias-example'>
                    <title>Defining and using an alias (PL variable)</title>
                    <screen>
    * q = SELECT COUNT(*) FROM mytable
    *q;
    *q WHERE mass > 200;</screen>
                </example>
            </para><simpara>
                If you put variable definitions into the SQL file
                <filename>auto.sql</filename> in your home directory, those
                aliases/variables will always be available for interactive use.
        </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <simpara>
            See the <link linkend='pl-section' endterm='pl-title'/> section 
            below for information on using variables in other ways, and 
            information on the other PL commands and features.
        </simpara>
        <section><title>SQL History</title>
        <simpara>
            The SQL history shown by the \s command, and used by other commands,
            is truncated to 20 entries, since the utility comes from being 
            able to quickly view the history list.
            You can change the history length by setting the system property
            <literal>sqltool.historyLength</literal> to an integer like
            <screen>
java -Dsqltool.historyLength=40 -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid</screen>
        </simpara> <simpara>
            The SQL history list explicitly does not contain Special, Buffer,
            or PL commands.
            It only contains SQL commands, valid or invalid, successful or 
            unsuccessful.
            The reason for including bad SQL commands is so that you can 
            recall and edit them if you want to.
            The same applies to the editing buffer (which is element 0
            of the history).
        </simpara>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section><title>Raw mode</title>
        <para>
            If for some reason you want SqlTool to process your commands as 
            if it were reading an SQL file (i.e., no startup banner,
            no command prompts, no Buffer/history commands, aborting upon
            failure by default, allow blank lines with SQL statements),
            then specify a SQL filepath of "-", like
        <informalexample><screen>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid -</screen>
        </informalexample></para><para>
            This is very useful in (at least) two situations.
            This is how you would pipe input into SqlTool, which is 
            extremely useful in shell scripts where the SQL code is
            generated dynamically, like
        <example><title>Piping input into SqlTool</title><screen>
    echo "Some SQL commands with '$VARIABLES';" |
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid -</screen>
        </example></para><simpara>
            This is also a good way to test what SqlTool will do when it 
            encounters a specific command in a SQL file.
            You <emphasis>emulate</emphasis> SQL file execution while
            giving SqlTool commands interactively.
        </simpara>
    </section>

    <section id='nonint-section'>
        <title id='nonint-title'>Non-Interactive</title>
        <simpara>
            Read the <link linkend='int-section' endterm='int-title'/>
            section if you have not already, 
            because much of what is in this section builds upon that.
            Even if your plans are to run SqlTool non-interactively, you 
            should really learn to run it interactively because it's such a 
            powerful debugging tool, and you can use it to prototype sql 
            scripts.
        </simpara>
        <important><simpara>
            If you're doing data updates, remember to issue a commit command
            or use the <literal>--autoCommit</literal> switch.
        </simpara></important>
        <simpara>
            As you'll see, SqlTool has many features that are very 
            convenient for scripting.  But what really makes it superior for
            automation tasks (as compared to SQL tools from other vendors)
            is the ability to reliably detect errors and to control JDBC
            transactions.
        </simpara>
        <section><title>Giving SQL on the Command Line</title>
            <para>
                If you just have a couple SQL commands to run, you can run them 
                directly from the comand-line or from a shell script without an 
                SQL file, like this.
            <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar --noinput --sql 'SQL statement;' urlid</screen>
            </informalexample></para><para>
                Since SqlTool executes SQL statements only when a statement 
                line is terminated with ";", you can only execute more than one 
                SQL statement this way if your OS shell has some mechanism to 
                pass linebreaks in arguments through to the target program.
                With any Bourne-compatible shell, you can include linebreaks in 
                the SQL statements like this.
            <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar --noinput --sql 'SQL statement;' urlid '
    SQL statement number one;
    SQL statement
        number two;
    SQL statement three;
' urlid</screen>
            </informalexample></para><simpara>
                If you don't give the <literal>--noinput</literal> switch, then 
                after executing the given statements, an interactive session 
                will be started.
            </simpara><para>
                The <emphasis>--sql</emphasis> switch is very useful for 
                setting shell variables to the output of SQL Statements, like 
                this.
            <informalexample><programlisting>
    # A shell script
    USERCOUNT=`java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar --noinput --sql 'select count(*) from usertbl;' urlid` || {
        # Handle the SqlTool error
    }
    echo "There are $USERCOUNT users registered in the database."
    [ "$USECOUNT" -gt 3 ] &amp;&amp; {   # If there are more than 3 users registered
        # Some conditional shell scripting</programlisting></informalexample>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section><title>SQL Files</title>
            <simpara>
                Just give paths to sql text file(s) on the command line after 
                the <emphasis>urlid</emphasis>.
            </simpara><para>
                Often, you will want to redirect output to a file, like
            <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar sql... > /tmp/log.sql 2>&amp;1</screen>
            </informalexample></para><simpara>
                (Skip the "2>&amp;1" if you're on Windows).
            </simpara><simpara>
                You can also execute SQL files from an interactive session with
                the "\i"' Special Command,
                but be aware that the default behavior in an interactive 
                session is to continue upon errors.
                If the SQL file was written without any concern for error
                handling, then the file will continue to execute after errors
                occur.
                You could run <literal>\* false</literal> before 
                <literal>\i filename</literal>, but then your SqlTool session
                will exit if an error is encountered in the SQL file.
                If you have an SQL file without error handling, and you want
                to abort that file when an error occurs, but not exit 
                SqlTool, the easiest way to accomplish this is usually to add
                <literal>\* false</literal> to the top of the script.
            </simpara><simpara>
                If you specify multiple SQL files on the command-line, the
                default behavior is to exit SqlTool if any of the SQL files
                encounters an error.
            </simpara><simpara>
                <emphasis role='bold'>
                SQL files themselves have ultimate control over error handling.
                </emphasis>
                Regardless of what command-line options are set, or what 
                commands you give interactively, if a SQL file gives error
                handling statements, they will take precedence.
            </simpara><simpara>
                You can also use \i in SQL files.
                This results in nested SQL files.
            </simpara><simpara>
                You can use the following SQL file,
                <filename>sample.sql</filename>, which resides in the
                <filename>src/org/hsqldb/sample</filename> directory of your
                HSQLDB distribution.
                It contains SQL as well as Special Commands making good
                use of most of the Special Commands documented below.
            </simpara>
            <programlisting>&sample.sql-cdata;</programlisting>
            <para>
                You can execute this SQL file with a Memory Only database with 
                a command like
            <informalexample><programlisting>
    java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar  --sql "create user 'tomcat' password 'x';" mem path/to/hsqldb/src/org/hsqldb/sample/sample.sql</programlisting>
            </informalexample>
            </para><simpara>
                (The <literal>--sql "create..."</literal> arguments create an
                account which the script uses).
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Optimally Compatible SQL Files</title>
            <simpara>
                If you want your SQL scripts optimally compatible among other
                SQL tools, then don't use any Special or PL Commands.
                SqlTool has default behavior which I think is far superior to 
                the other SQL tools, but you will have to disable these 
                defaults in order to have optimally compatible behavior.
            </simpara><para>
                These switches provide compatibilty at the cost of poor 
                control and error detection.
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <simpara>
                            --continueOnErr
                        </simpara> <simpara>
                            The output will still contain error messages about
                            everything that SqlTool doesn't like
                            (malformatted commands, SQL command failures, 
                            empty SQL commands), but SqlTool will continue to
                            run.
                            Errors will not cause rollbacks (but that won't
                            matter because of the following setting).
                        </simpara>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem><simpara>--autoCommit</simpara></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para><simpara>
                You don't have to worry about accidental expansion of 
                PL variables, since SqlTool will never expand PL variables
                if you don't set any variables on the command line, or give 
                any "* " PL commands.
                (And you could not have "* " commands in a compatible SQL 
                file).
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section><title>Comments</title>
            <simpara>
                SQL comments of the form <literal>/*...*/</literal> must begin
                where a (SQL/Special/Buffer/PL) Command could begin, and they
                end with the very first "*/" (regardless of quotes, nesting,
                etc.
                You may have as many blank lines as you want inside of a
                comment.
            </simpara>
            <example><title>Valid comment example</title><programlisting>
    SELECT count(*) FROM atable;
    /* Lots of
     comments interspersed among
     several lines */   SELECT count(*)
    FROM btable;</programlisting>
            </example>
            <simpara>
                Notice that a command can start immediate after the comment
                ends.
            </simpara>
            <example><title>Invalid comment example</title><programlisting>
    SELECT count(*) FROM
    /* atable */
    btable;</programlisting>
            </example>
            <simpara>
                This comment is invalid because you could not start another
                command at the comment location (because it is within an SQL
                Statement).
            </simpara>
            <simpara>
                You can try using <literal>/*...*/</literal> in other locations,
                and <literal>--</literal> style SQL comments, but SqlTool will
                not treat them as comments.
                If they occur within an SQL Statment, SqlTool will pass them to
                the database engine, and the DB engine will determine whether
                to parse them as comments.
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Special Commands and Buffer Commands in SQL Files</title>
            <simpara>
                Don't use Buffer Commands in your sql files, because they won't 
                work.
                Buffer Commands are for interactive use only.
            </simpara>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry><term>\q [abort message]</term><listitem><para>
                    Be aware that the \q command will cause SqlTool to 
                    completely exit.
                    If a script <filename>x.sql</filename> has a \q command in
                    it, then it doesn't matter if the script is executed like
                    <screen>
    java -jar .../hsqldb.jar urlid a.sql x.sql z.sql</screen> or if you use
                    \i to read it in interactively, or if another SQL file
                    uses \i to nest it.
                    If \q is encountered, SqlTool will quit.
                    See the <link linkend='pl-section' endterm='pl-title'/> 
                    section for commands to abort an SQL file (or even parts
                    of an SQL file) without causing SqlTool to exit.
                </para><simpara>
                    \q takes an optional argument, which is an abort message.
                    If you give an abort message, the message is displayed to
                    the user and SqlTool will exit with a failure status.
                    If you give no abort message, then SqlTool will exit 
                    quietly with successful status.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>\p [text to print]</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Print the given string to stdout.
                    Just give "\p" alone to print a blank line.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>\i /path/to/file.sql</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Include another SQL file at this location.
                    You can use this to nest SQL files.
                    For database installation scripts I often have a master
                    SQL file which includes all of the other SQL files in the
                    correct sequence.
                    Be aware that the current continue-upon-error behavior
                    will apply to included files until such point as the SQL
                    file runs its own error handling commands.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>\H</term><listitem><para>
                    Toggle HTML output mode.
                    If you redirect output to a file, this can make a long
                    session log much easier to view.
                    This will HTML-ify the entire session.
                    For example,
                    <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid filepath1.sql... > /tmp/log.html 2>&amp;1</screen>
                    </informalexample>
                    (See the
                    <link linkend='report-section' endterm='report-title'/> 
                    section about how to easily store just the query output
                    to file.)
                </para></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>\a [true|false]</term><listitem><simpara>
                    This turns on and off SQL transaction autocommits.
                    Auto-commit defaults to false, but you can change that
                    behavior by using the <literal>--autoCommit</literal>
                    command-line switch.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>\* [true|false]</term><listitem><simpara>
                    A "true" setting tells SqlTool to continue when errors are 
                    encountered.
                    The current transaction will not be rolled back upon SQL
                    errors, so if \* is true, then run the
                    <literal>ROLLCACK;</literal> command yourself if that's 
                    what you want to happen.
                    The default for interactive use is to continue upon error, 
                    but the default for non-interactive use is to abort upon 
                    error.
                    You can override this behavior by using the
                    <literal>--continueOnErr</literal> or the
                    <literal>--abortOnErr</literal> command-line switch.
                    </simpara><simpara>
                    With database setup scripts, I usually find it convenient 
                    to set "true" before dropping tables (so that things will 
                    continue if the tables aren't there), then set it back to 
                    false so that real errors are caught.
                    <literal>DROP TABLE tablename IF EXISTS;</literal>
                    is a more elegant, but less portable, way to accomplish
                    the same thing.
                    </simpara>
                    <tip><simpara>
                        It depends on what you want your SQL files to do, of
                        course, but I usually want my SQL files to abort when
                        an error is encountered, without necessarily killing 
                        the SqlTool session.
                        If this is the behavior that you want, then
                        put an explicit <literal>\* false</literal>
                        at the top of your SQL file and turn on
                        continue-upon-error only for sections where you really
                        want to permit errors, or where you are using PL
                        commands to handle errors manually.
                        This will give the desired behavior whether your 
                        script is called by
                        somebody interactively, from the SqlTool command-line, 
                        or included in another SQL file (i.e. nested).
                    </simpara></tip><important><simpara>
                        The default settings are usually best for people who 
                        don't want to put in any explicit \* or error handling 
                        code at all.
                        If you run SQL files from the SqlTool command line,
                        then any errors will cause SqlTool to roll back and
                        abort immediately.
                        If you run SqlTool interactively and invoke SQL files
                        with \i commands, the scripts will continue to run
                        upon errors (and will not roll back).
                        This behavior was chosen because there are lots of
                        SQL files out there that produce errors which can be
                        ignored; but we don't want to ignore errors that a
                        user won't see.
                        I reiterate that any and all of this behavior can (and 
                        often should) be changed by Special Commands run in 
                        your interactive shell or in the SQL files.
                        Only you know whether errors in your SQL files can
                        safely be ignored.
                    </simpara></important>
                </listitem></varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section><title>Automation</title>
            <simpara>
                SqlTool is ideal for mission-critical automation because,
                unlike other SQL tools, SqlTool returns a dependable exit 
                status and gives you control over error handling and SQL 
                transactions.
                Autocommit is off by default, so you can build a completely
                dependable solution by intelligently using \* commands 
                (Continue upon Errors) and commit statements, and by
                verifying exit statuses.
            </simpara> <simpara>
                Using the SqlTool Procedural Language, you have ultimate
                control over program flow, and you can use variables for
                database input and output as well as for many other purposes.
                See the <link linkend='pl-section' endterm='pl-title'/>
                section.
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section><title>Getting Interactive Functionality with SQL Files</title>
            <para>
                Some script developers may run into cases where they want to 
                run with sql files but they alwo want SqlTool's interactive 
                behavior.
                For example, they may want to do command recall in the sql file,
                or they may want to log SqlTool's command-line prompts (which 
                are not printed in non-interactive mode).
                In this case, do not give the sql file(s) as an argument to 
                SqlTool, but pipe them in instead, like
            <informalexample><screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid &lt; filepath1.sql &gt; /tmp/log.html 2&gt;&amp;1</screen>
            </informalexample>
                or
            <informalexample><screen>
cat filepath1.sql... |
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid &gt; /tmp/log.html 2&gt;&amp;1</screen>
            </informalexample>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id='charencoding-section'><title id='charencoding-title'>
                Character Encoding</title>
            <para>
                SqlTool defaults to the US-ASCII character set (for reading).
                You can use another character set by setting the system 
                property <property>sqltool.charset</property>, like
            <informalexample><screen>
java -Dsqltool.charset=UTF-8 -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar urlid filepath1.sql...</screen>
            </informalexample></para><simpara>
                You can also set this per urlid in the SqlTool configuration 
                file.
                See the <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/>
                section about that.
            </simpara>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id='report-section'>
        <title id='report-title'>Generating Text or HTML Reports</title>
        <simpara>
            This section is about making a file containing the output of 
            database queries.
            You can generate reports by using operating system facilities
            such as redirection, tee, and cutting and pasting.
            But it is much easier to use the "\o" and "\H" special commands.
        </simpara> <procedure>
            <title>Writing query output to an external file</title>
            <step><simpara>
                By default, everthing will be done in plain text.
                If you want your report to be in HTML format, then give the
                special command <literal>\H</literal>.
                If you do so, you will probably want to use filenames with an
                suffix of ".html" or ".htm" instead of ".txt" in the next step.
            </simpara></step> <step><simpara>
                Run the command <literal>\o path/to/reportfile.txt</literal>.
                From this point on, output from your queries will be appended
                to the specified file.
                (I.e. another <emphasis>copy</emphasis> of the output is
                generated.)
                This way you can continue to monitor or use output as usual as
                the report is generated.
            </simpara></step> <step><simpara>
                When you want SqlTool to stop writing to the file, run
                <literal>\o</literal> (or just quit SqlTool if you have no 
                other work to do).
            </simpara></step> <step><simpara>
                If you turned on HTML mode with <literal>\H</literal> before,
                you can run <literal>\H</literal> again to turn it back off,
                if you wish.
            </simpara></step>
        </procedure>
        <simpara>
            It is not just the output of "SELECT" statements that will make
            it into the report file, but
            <itemizedlist>
                <title>Kinds of output that get teed to \o files</title>
                <listitem><simpara>
                    Output of SELECT statements.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    Output of all "\d" Special Commands.
                    (I.e., "\dt", "\dv", etc., and "\d OBJECTNAME").
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    Output of "\p" Special Commands.
                    You will want to use this to add titles, and perhaps
                    spacing, for the output of individual queries.
                </simpara></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Other output will go to your screen or stdout, but will not make
            it into the report file.
            Be aware that no error messages will go into the report file.
            If SqlTool is run non-interactively (including if you give any
            SQL file(s) on the command line), SqlTool will abort with an error
            status if errors are encountered.
            The right way to handle errors is to check the SqlTool exit status.
            (The described error-handling behavior can be modified with
            SqlTool command-line switches and Special Commands).
        </simpara> <warning><simpara>
            Remember that \o <emphasis>appends</emphasis> to the named file.
            If you want a new file, then use a new file name or remove the
            targe file ahead of time.
        </simpara></warning><tip><simpara>
            So that I don't end up with a bunch of junk in my report file, I
            usually leave \o off while I perfect my SQL.  With \o off,
            I perfect the SQL query until it produces on my screen exactly
            what I want saved to file.
            At this point I turn on \o and run ":;" to repeat the last SQL
            command.
            If I have several complex queries to run, I turn \o off and
            repeat until I'm finished.
            (Every time you turn \o on, it will append to the file, just
            like we need).
            </simpara><simpara>
            Usually it doesn't come to mind that I need a wider screen until
            a query produces lines that are too long.
            In this case, stretch your window and repeat the last command with
            the ":;" Buffer Command.
        </simpara></tip>
    </section>

    <section id='pl-section'>
        <title id='pl-title'>Procedural Language</title>
        <subtitle>Aka PL</subtitle>
        <simpara>
            Most importantly, run <filename>SqlTool</filename> interactively 
            and give the "* ?" command to see what PL commands are available to 
            you.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            PL variables will only be expanded after you run a PL command (or 
            set variable(s) from the command-line).
            We only want to turn on variable expansion if the user wants
            variable expansion.
            People who don't use PL don't have to worry about strings getting
            accidentally expanded.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            For all PL commands (other than plain "*") the leading "*" must
            be followed by whitespace.
            The only reason for this requirement is to provide for
            aliases, i.e., the ability to short-cut
            <literal>*VARNAME</literal> for <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal> at
            the beginning of a command.
            Therefore, "*X" is an alias whereas "* X" is a PL command.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            The command "*" is an exception to this rule.
            it doesn't matter whether you put white space after it.
            All other PL commands imply the "*" command, so you only need to 
            use the "*" statement if your script uses PL variables
            and it is possible that no variables may be set before-hand (and
            no PL commands have been run previously).
            In this case, without "*", your script would silently use a
            literal value like "*{x}" instead of trying to expand it.
            With a preceding "*" command, PL will notice that the variable
            <literal>x</literal> has not been set and will generate an error.
            (If x had been set here will be no issue because setting a
            variable automatically turns on PL variable expansion).
        </simpara> <para>
            Aliasing may only be used for SQL statements.
            You can define variables for everything in a Special or PL Command,
            except for the very first character ("\" or "*").
            Therefore, you can use variables but not aliasing in Special and
            PL Commands.
            Here is a hyperbolically impractical example to show the extent to
            which PL variables can be used in Special commands even though you
            can not use them as aliases.
            <programlisting>
        sql> * qq = p Hello Butch
        sql> \*{qq} done now
        Hello Butch done now</programlisting>
        </para>
        <section>
            <title>Variables</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><simpara>
                    Use the <literal>* list</literal> command to list some or
                    all variables and their values.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    You can set variables using the
                    <literal>* VARNAME = value</literal> command.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    You can also set variables using the 
                    <literal>--setvar</literal> command-line switch.
                    I give a very brief but useful example of this below.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    Variables are always expanded in SQL, Special, and PL
                    commands if they are written like
                    <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal>
                    (assuming that a PL command has been run previously).
                    Your SQL scripts can give good feedback by echoing the
                    value of variables with the "\p" special command.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    Variables written like <literal>*VARNAME</literal> are
                    expanded if they <emphasis>begin</emphasis> an SQL
                    Statement.
                    (They must also be followed by whitespace or terminate the
                    Statement).
                    I usually refer to this use of PL variables as
                    <emphasis>aliasing</emphasis>.
                    If the value of a variable is an entire SQL command, you
                    generally do not want to include the terminating ";" in
                    the value.
                    There is an example of this 
                    <link linkend='alias-example'>above</link>.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><simpara>
                    Variables are normally written like 
                    <literal>*VARNAME</literal> in logical expressions to
                    prevent them from being evaluated too early.
                    See below about logical expressions.
                </simpara></listitem> <listitem><para>
                    You can't do math with expression variables, but you
                    can get functionality like the traditional
                    <literal>for (i = 0; i &lt; x; i++)</literal> by appending
                    to a variable and testing the string length, like
                    <programlisting>
    * while (*i &lt; ${x})
        * i = *{i}.</programlisting>
                    <literal>i</literal> will be a growing line of dots.
                </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <simpara>
                Here is a short SQL file that gives the specified user write
                permissions on some application tables.
            </simpara>
            <example><title>Simple SQL file using PL</title>
                <programlisting>
    /*
       grantwrite.sql

       Run SqlTool like this:
           java -jar path/to/hsqldb.jar -setvar USER=debbie grantwrite.sql
     */

    /* Explicitly turn on PL variable expansion, in case no variables have
       been set yet.  (Only the case if user did not set USER).
    */
    *

    GRANT all ON book TO *{USER};
    GRANT all ON category TO *{USER};</programlisting>
            </example>
            <simpara>
                Note that this script will work for any (existing) user just
                by supplying a different user name on the command-line.
                I.e., no need to modify the tested and proven script.
                There is no need for a <literal>commit</literal> statement
                in this SQL file since no DML is done.
                If the script is accidentally run without setting the
                USER variable, SqlTool will give a very clear notificaton of
                that.
            </simpara> <simpara>
                The purpose of unsetting the INIT variable is just to 
                initialize PL so that the *{USER} variables will be expanded.
                (This would not be necessary if the USER variable, or any
                other variable, were set, but we don't want to depend upon 
                that).
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Logical Expressions</title>
            <simpara>
                Logical expressions occur only inside of logical expression
                parentheses in PL statements.
                For example, <literal>if (*var1 > astring)</literal> and
                <literal>while (*checkvar)</literal>.
                (The parentheses after "foreach" do not enclose a logical
                expression, they just enclose a list).
            </simpara> <simpara>
                There is a critical difference between 
                <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal> and <literal>*VARNAME</literal>
                inside logical expressions.
                <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal> is expanded one time when the
                parser first encounters the logical expression.
                <literal>*VARNAME</literal> is re-expanded every time that the
                expression is evaluated.
                So, you would never want to code
                <literal>* while (*{X} &lt; 5)</literal> because the statement
                will always be true or always be false.
                (I.e. the following block will loop infinitely or will never
                run).
            </simpara> <simpara>
                Don't use quotes or whitespace of any kind in
                <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal> variables in expressions.
                (They would expand and then the expression would most likely
                no longer be a valid expression as listed in the table below).
                Quotes and whitespace are fine in <literal>*VARNAME</literal>
                variables, but it is the entire value that will be used in
                evaluations, regardless of whether quotes match up, etc.
                I.e. quotes and whitespace are not <emphasis>special</emphasis>
                to the token evaluator.
            </simpara>
            <variablelist>
                <title>Logical Operators</title>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN</term><listitem><simpara>
                    The token may be a literal, a <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal>
                    which is expanded early, or a *VARNAME which is expanded 
                    late.
                    (You usually do not want to use 
                    <literal>*{VARNAME}</literal> in logical expressions).
                    False if the token is not set, empty, or "0".
                    True otherwise.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN1 == TOKEN2</term><listitem><simpara>
                    True if the two tokens are equivalent "strings".
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN1 &lt;&gt; TOKEN2</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Ditto.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN1 &gt;&lt; TOKEN2</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Ditto.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN1 &gt; TOKEN2</term><listitem><simpara>
                    True if the TOKEN1 string is longer than TOKEN2 or is
                    the same length but is greater according to a string sort.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>TOKEN1 &lt; TOKEN2</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Similarly to TOKEN1 &gt; TOKEN2.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>! LOGICAL_EXPRESSION</term><listitem><simpara>
                    Logical negation of any of the expressions listed above.
                </simpara></listitem></varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            <simpara>
                *VARNAMEs in logical expressions, where the VARNAME variable
                is not set, evaluate to an empty string.
                Therefore <literal>(*UNSETVAR = 0)</literal> would be false,
                even though <literal>(*UNSETVAR)</literal> by itself is false
                and <literal>(0)</literal> by itself is false.
            </simpara> <simpara>
                When developing scripts, you definitely use SqlTool 
                interactively to verify that SqlTool evaluates logical 
                expressions as you expect.
                Just run <literal>* if</literal> commands that print something
                (i.e. \p) if the test expression is true.
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Flow Control</title>
            <simpara>
                Flow control works by conditionally executing blocks of 
                Commands according to conditions specified by logical 
                expressions.
            </simpara> <simpara>
                The conditionally executed blocks are called 
                <emphasis>PL Blocks</emphasis>.
                These PL Blocks always occur between a PL flow control 
                statement (like <literal>* foreach, *while, * if</literal>)
                and a corresponding <literal>* end</literal> PL Command
                (like <literal>* end foreach</literal>).
            </simpara> <caution><simpara>
                Be aware that the PL block reader is ignorant about SQL 
                statements and comments when looking for the end of the block.
                It just looks for lines beginning with some specific PL commands.
                Therefore, if you put a comment line before a PL statement, 
                or if a line of a multi-line SQL statement has a line beginning
                with a PL command, things may break.
                </simpara> <simpara>
                I am not saying that you shouldn't use PL commands or SQL
                commands inside of PL blocks-- you definitely should!
                I'm saying that in PL blocks you should not have lines inside 
                of SQL statments or comments which could be mistaken for PL 
                commands.
                (Especially, "commenting out" PL end statements will not work
                if you leave <literal>* end</literal> at the beginning of the
                line).
                </simpara> <simpara>
                (This limitation will very likely be removed in a future 
                version of SqlTool).
            </simpara></caution> <simpara>
                The values of control variables for foreach and while PL
                blocks will change as expected.
            </simpara> <simpara>
                There are <literal>* break</literal> and 
                <literal>* continue</literal>, which work as any shell
                scripter would expect them to.
                The <literal>* break</literal> command can also be used to
                quit the current SQL file without triggering any error 
                processing.
                (I.e. processing will continue with the next line in the 
                <emphasis>including</emphasis> SQL file or interactive 
                session, or with the next SQL file if you supplied multiple on 
                the command-line).
            </simpara>
        </section>
        <para>
            Below is an example SQL File that shows how to use most PL 
            features.  If you have a question about how to use a particular PL 
            feature, check this example before asking for help.
            This file resides in the
            <filename>src/org/hsqldb/sample</filename> directory with the
            name <filename>pl.sql</filename>.
            Definitely give it a run, like <screen>
java -jar $HSQLDB_HOME/lib/hsqldb.jar mem $HSQLDB_HOME/src/org/hsqldb/sample/pl.jar</screen>
        </para>
        <example><title>SQL File showing use of most PL features</title>
            <programlisting>&pl.sql-cdata;</programlisting>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Using hsqlsqltool.jar</title>
        <simpara>
            This section is only for those users who want to use SqlTool
            but without the overhead of hsqldb.jar.
        </simpara><simpara>
            If you do not need to directly use JDBC URLs like
            <literal>jdbc:hsqldb:mem:</literal> + something,
            <literal>jdbc:hsqldb:file:</literal> + something, or
            <literal>jdbc:hsqldb:res:</literal> + something,
            then you can use <filename>hsqlsqltool.jar</filename> in place of
            the much larger <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename> file.
            <filename>hsqlsqltool.jar</filename> will work for all JDBC
            databases other than HSQLDB Memory-only and In-process databases
            (the latter are fine if you access them via a HSQLB Server or
            WebServer).
            You will have to supply the JDBC driver for non-HSQLDB URLs.
        </simpara><simpara>
            The HSQLDB distribution doesn't "come with" a pre-built 
            <filename>hsqlsqltool.jar</filename> file.
            I recommend that you either download the Java 1.4 jar at
            <ulink url='http://admc.com/dist/hsqlsqltool-1.7.2.jar'/>
            (by right-clicking and downloading if you're reading this with a
            web browser), or build the <emphasis>jarsqltool</emphasis> target, 
            as explained in the 
            <link linkend='building-appendix' endterm='building-title'/>
            appendix.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            If you are using the HSQLDB JDBC driver (i.e., you're connecting
            up to a URL like jdbc:hsqldb:hsql + something or
            jdbc:hsqldb:http + something), you run SqlTool exactly as with
            hsqldb.jar except you use the file path to your hsqlsqltool.jar
            file (for example, <filename>hsqlsqltool-1.7.2.jar</filename>)
            instead of the path to hsqldb.jar.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            If you are using a non-HSQLDB JDBC driver, follow the instructions
            at the end of the
            <link linkend='baremin-section' endterm='baremin-title'/> section,
            but use your hsqlsqltool jar file in place of
            <filename>hsqldb.jar</filename>.
        </simpara>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Unit Testing SqlTool</title>
        <simpara>
            A unit testing framework is in place.
            This assures the robustness of SqlTool.
            See the file <filename>testrun/sqltool/readme.txt</filename>
            for instructions on running, modifying, or creating unit
            tests.
            To create a new unit test, you create a SQL file and embed
            metacommands in the SQL file inside of comments.
            The metacommands tell the test harness
            (<classname>org.hsqldb.test.SqlToolHarness</classname>)
            how to run SqlTool (like with what arguments) and what
            output to expect (i.e. the test criteria).
            You can run tests without JUnit, or you can make a JUnit
            wrapper in the normal fashion.  Any SQL test file can
            be added to our JUnit SqlTool test suite by just adding
            the SQL file name and description to the 
            <filename>testrun/sqltool/*.list</filename> file for the 
            desired JUnit test method.
        </simpara> <simpara>
            (The SqlTool unit tests require java 1.4).
        </simpara>
    </section>
</chapter>
